A Guide to the Papers of the Janney and Related Gilmour and Pollock Families 1695(1755-1944)1981
Special Collections Department, University of Virginia Library
Letters, 1929-1938, to Nancy Lee (Janney) Gilmour from her sister-in-law, Lucy (Stevenson) Janney relate news of family. On January 13, 1935, Baltimore, she relates news of her son Robert [Stevenson Janney] and his education and work and her own work [weaving], making socks, sweaters and fishnet scarves. A letter of October 7, 1935 gives news of Robert at Princeton University. In a letter of March 6, 1938, The St. Francis, Union Square, San Francisco, she writes about hearing a sermon of C[harles] R[osenbury] Erdman (1866-1960) of Princeton Seminary at the Calvary Presbyterian Church and relates Robert's visits to the surrounding areas.
Letters, 1929-1944, to Nancy Lee (Janney) Gilmour from her brother, Thomas Gordon Janney, are chiefly written from his home in Chicago, Illinois. On June 20, 1929, he inquires about her European trip and mentions a Chicago horse, "Reigh Count," the second place runner in the Ascot Gold Cup. In a letter of April 17, 1934, he is busy with the spring season adjustments of coke prices and codes and labor studies. A letter of June 20, 1934 explains in detail how to connect an indoor aerial up to the radio. On September 19, 1934, he inquires about a Mr. Eisenhard and whether or not he is Jewish, commenting that "they are so prominent now in administration circles that it is no doubt an honor to entertain one." He also mentions "Willie" Metzger, who sees the wisdom of being very stern with those criminals who drive when intoxicated, and Shirley Temple. A letter of November 17, 1934 relates news of the apple business. On January 31, 1935, he gives advice to their sister, Lilias, as general manager of a building. A March 19, 1934 letter relates that "everything is still strained & disturbed in business circles & outlook anything but reassuring." On June 10, 1935, Gordon reminisces about Wilkesboro near the headwaters of the Yadkin River which was the terminus of his first job -- the survey and construction of a railroad from Winston-Salem to Wilkesboro. He also refers to the Supreme Court decision putting the National Recovery Administration (N.R.A.) where it belongs and how it will help business if the good features can be retained. On June 27, 1935, he mentions the visit of M'Cready Sykes (1869-1952) who spoke admiringly of Robert [Stevenson Janney]. A letter of September 25, 1935, he has come east to Leesburg on business brought about by the threat of the coal strike; he mentions a visit to Spa-Valley and Crozet over arrangements for apple storage. A January 27, 1936 letter discusses the death of "Harry" [Henry B. Rust] (1872-1935) and the funeral held at Calvary Episcopal Church and includes an obituary, also mentioning his parents Ida Lee and Armistead T. Rust. Also mentioned are the Spa-Valley outlook not being as good as New York and export prices being so low that little fruit is moving. On March 23, 1936, he gives news of cases of influenza and pneumonia and prevalent floods. In a letter of August 9, 1944, Gordon mentions there is not enough rain to save the corn crops in the area.
Letters, 1898-1946, to Abram David Pollock Janney and Lucy (Stevenson) Janney cover a variety of topics. There is a gossipy letter, October 7, 1898, from Berina Gilmour, to A. D. P. Janney, Virginia Military Institute, Lexington, discussing mutual male acquaintances that are V.M.I. cadets. On October 13, 1898, Charles P. Janney, Leesburg, writes to his son concerning his promotion to First Sergeant and encouraging his studies. On January 4 & 23, 1899, Janney writes to his son at V. M. I. concerning the news that General Shipp has dismissed the entire First Class as a disciplinary action and actions taken in regard to the First Class and giving advice on daily study to prepare for examinations. On February 25, 1900, Nancy Lee Janney, Leesburg, writes to her brother with a description of the wedding of "Lalla" and other local news. A letter, March 20, 1925, from Harris E[lliott]Kirk (1872- 1953), Minister, Franklin Street Presbyterian Church, Baltimore, expresses sympathy over the death of Charles Phillips Janney. There is a Christmas greeting, 1926, from Anne (Morson) and Francis Lee Stuart (1866-1935). On January 12, 1927, Thomas Gordon Janney, Chicago, discusses his illness due to the extraction of a wisdom tooth and mentions Turn of the Century [first volume of Our Times, the United States, 1900-1925] by Mark Sullivan (1874-1952). A February 15, 1928 letter from Nancy Lee Janney discusses her activities in Sicily and Taormina, Italy. A March 14, 1928 letter from Lilias Janney discusses activities in Florence, Italy, including a drive to Il Miniato and the Cascine, and future plans for visits to the Riviera, Nice, Milan, Venice, and Paris. A May 7, [1928] letter discusses activities in Paris and touring the countryside. A May 13, 1928 letter mentions the purchase of red copper water bottles in Vienna. On June 17, 1928, Edinburgh, Scotland, Lilias discusses her activities in London, including seeing the King [George V] and Queen [Mary] and Princess Mary and the Prince of Wales at the Trophy of the Colours, watching the procession from St. James Park. On December 7th and 18th, Harris E. Kirk sends church memorabilia about Robert Stevenson Janney.
Correspondence and papers, 1852-1923, of Charles Phillips Janney consists of letters to and from Janney, financial and legal papers, and miscellaneous papers. Letters from Janney discuss politics and legal and personal matters. On September 17, 1878, he writes to "Dear Charlie" providing support in his determination "to abandon the use of drink..."; that the temperance movement in Loudoun County has assumed formidable proportions; suggesting that he connects himself with the order here; and that he will consider a partnership after the experiment proceeds for a year. There is a letter [1884 or 1892] "To The Honorable Grover Cleveland President Elect" requesting that he consider John Randolph Tucker (1823-1897) for Attorney General and praising the character and professionalism of Tucker. A letter to the editor, September 3, 1901, concerns those who desire him to represent them in the State Senate and his decline of the offer. Letters of March 22, 1922 and October 4, 1923 concern Janney family properties, "Leeton Forest" and King Street property. On December 31, 1917, in a letter to Albert Shaw (1857-1947), Janney comments on President Woodrow Wilson as being a real leader to the American people. There is an undated letter [ca. 1921] concerning the presentation of an Arbor Vitae tree to Hampden-Sydney College on behalf of Lois I. (Kimsey) Marshall, wife of Thomas R. Marshall, the recent Vice-President of the United States. On September 17, 1923, Janney writes to Henry J. Nichols, recalling an incident as a child in Hillsboro during the Presidential Campaign of 1844, mentioning his father, James Craik Janney (1804-1878) and Lewis McKenzie (1810- 1895), and a conveyance returning from a Whig meeting in Maryland.
There are also letters, 1865-1923, to Charles Phillips Janney and Nannie Lee (Pollock) Janney from family, friends and professional contacts. On July 26, 1865, H. B. Miller, Culpeper County, reports that only secessionists are in the political field for the elections for county officers and that the Union men are still hated. On January 20, 1866, Samuel McPherson Janney (1801-1880), Washington, D. C., a Unionist during the war, reports on efforts to be indemnified for losses sustained by the family during the Civil War; mentions consulting several prominent statesmen, including [Henry Bowen] Anthony (1815-1884), [Daniel] Clark (1809-1891), C[olumbus] Delano (1809-1896), Charles Edward Phelps (1833-1908), [Noah Haynes] Swayne (1804-1884), and [Edwin Hanson] Webster (1829-1893). A letter of February 18, 1868, from D. W. Taylor, Alexandria, concerns Miss Fannie Pollock, whom he judges as "a true woman" and believes that she "has good ideas as to what should constitute a true woman"; and, contains a discussion of relationships between men and women and how their opinions on certain subjects may vary. There is a letter, January 22, 1884, from James S. Porter, pastor, about the Gum Spring Methodist Church at Gainesville. On June 23, 1897, M. O. Hawkins, "Hanover Construction Company/Builders of the Montgomery Division of the Mobile & Ohio Railroad," Tuscaloosa, Alabama, writes concerning the hiring of an assistant engineer and his request for John [Janney] and the railroad company building 200 miles through Alabama. Letters, March 28, 1921 and January 16, 1922, concerning the Janney family and land patents are from Fairfax Harrison (1869-1938) and Richard Mott Janney. There are two letters, October 9 & 16, 1923, from James E. Galleher and W. Cary Galleher, Jr. of Richmond concerning the purchase of the King Street property in Leesburg.
Letters to Charles Phillips Janney from William Edward Dodd (1869-1940) concern the purchase, 1912-1913, and management, 1916-1925, of Middlebrook Farm, Round Hill, Virginia. A September 24, 1914 letter concerns the contract with Houghton Mifflin Company for Dodd's History of the United States. Letters from 1914-1916 concern the settlement of the Laura B. V. Gray land. On February 26 and April 28, 1916, Dodd at the University of Chicago, comments on events in Europe, mentioning the fight around Verdun and German ambitions, the cost to the French in holding back the Germans from Verdun, and the presence of Russians in France.
Letters, 1916-1924, to Charles Phillips Janney from Nancy Lee (Janney) Gilmour chiefly detail her visit to the Far East in 1918. In letters of January 27 and 31,1916, she writes from Philadelphia, Pennsylvania concerning people met and her activities, including a luncheon with the Arts Club, attending the Opera, a ball at the Ritz-Carlton and a Shakespeare party. On April 20, 1918, she writes onboard the S. S. Korea Maru about people onboard and the activities, including shuffleboard, bridge, and checkers. A May 26, 1918 letter describes travel in Korea, relating that they left Tokyo, Japan on an express train to Shimonoseki, Japan and viewed the countryside of Japan, passing Fuji, inlets of the sea, and cultivated lands. While traveling through Korea, they went through mountainous country, cultivated lands and wild countryside. On May 30, 1918, from Peking, China, Nancy discusses the breakdown of their train engine and the resultant delay at the station, after having crossed Manchuria. She mentions the station being full of Chinese soldiers walking up and down and a couple returning from Petrograd, where they had been through the Revolution. She also describes a tour of Peking, including Rickshaw, the Legation Quarter, and the Gate of the Tartar. In a letter of June 13, 1918, from Kyoto, Japan, she describes a trip from Seoul, Korea to Pusan, Korea, across the Sea of Japan, to Shimonoseki, Japan, and across the lake. She mentions the people on the train, including Bishop [Beverley Dandridge] Tucker (1846-1930), and notes the different expressions on the faces of the Christian Japanese. On June 20, 1918, from Tokyo, Japan, she discusses the visit of Prince Arthur to the Emperor. On August 18, 1918, Nancy is returning to the United States on the S. S. Kamo Maru with other members of her mission; she describes the ship and discusses people onboard. She also relates the tale of the Furgusons, missionaries from the west of China who were attacked by Chinese pirates. In a letter dated May 6, 1922, Norfolk, Virginia, she mentions the import of servants. There are two letters, February 12 and March 8, 1923, from Chicago, Illinois, discussing Bible School and various activities and people. Nancy writes a letter from Boston, Massachusetts, on the day of the death of Woodrow Wilson, February 3, 1924, expressing "It is sad to feel that the great leader-- at last is gaining his peace." On February 7, 1924, from Cambridge, Massachusetts, she mentions the funeral of Woodrow Wilson.
Letters, 1908, to Charles Phillips Janney from Lilias Janney and Nannie Lee (Pollock) Janney, are chiefly from Pasadena, California where Nannie Lee Janney is convalescing. Letters of February 6 & 8, 1908 give a description of the neighborhoods and the city of Pasadena and mentions activities such as seeing a Minstrel show, going to Redondo Beach, and driving to "Oak Knoll" and "Venice." Letters from Lilias during late February through late March discuss the failing health of her mother, Nannie Lee (Pollock) Janney. On April 19, 1916, Lilias writes from Tokyo, Japan, mentioning visits to the Tokyo Electric Car Station, Imperial University, cottage of Armistead and Margaret [at the University ?], the T. K. K. ships, the Embassy, Imperial Theatre, and "Cherry Blossom" Sunday at the park, as well as other activities and people.
Correspondence, 1896-1899, of John Janney, Jr. cover a variety of subjects. A letter of February 29, 1896, from his mother, Nannie Lee (Pollock) Janney, to Janney at Virginia Military Institute, give encouragement to keep up his studies, news of the health of Marshall and Harry [Henry B.] Rust, and news of family and friends. On April 7, 1896, his sister Lilias mentions going to the Yale concert and ball. On February 19, 1897, his aunt, Lily [Pollock], "Leeton Forest" supplies remedies for indigestion and sore throat. A letter of March 3, 1897 from his brother, Thomas Gordon Janney, suggests gargling with witch hazel for his sore throat and mentions a fifty per cent salary increase at the Baltimore and Ohio Railroad Company. Letters from his father, Charles Phillips Janney, enclose a pass, duly extended (January 1, 1897); discuss available teaching positions at the College of South Carolina, the Fishburn School, in Clarksville, Tennessee, and at Gambier (March 9, 1897); and, give news that Colonel Isaac Saunders, principal of the Danville Military Institute, always secures a West Point Army graduate (March 27, 1897). There are two letters, September 17 & 18, 1898, from John Janney, Jr. at the University of Virginia, to his mother, Nannie Lee (Pollock) Janney, mentioning a lecture on International Law by [Raleigh Colston] Minor (1869-1923), his matriculation for courses in Philosophy and Law, hearing Bishop [Alfred Magill] Randolph (1836- 1918) at the University Chapel, and attending the Y.M.C.A. reception.
Political papers, 1932 and 1959-1960, of John Janney, Jr. include a government document, Payment of Adjusted-Compensation Certificates, 1932; a Pioche Record editorial concerning Virginia and Massive Resistance (February 5, 1959); Janney's comments on Virginia and Massive Resistance (February 18, 1959); a Congressional Record re the question of forced racial integration (September 5, 1959); and, newspaper clipping re "Declaration of Principles of Virginia Voters" with a photograph of Janney (January 25, 1960).
Letters, 1834-1848, from Nathaniel E. Janney in St. Louis, Missouri, to James C. Janney, discuss family and financial affairs. On February 13, 1834, Janney writes concerning the accounts of distress in the money market in the northern cities and throughout the country, the memorials signed by citizens to restore the deposits [Federal funds on deposit in the United States Bank and distributed to state banks by President Andrew Jackson], and the failure of numerous New York businesses, and gives advice on holding onto flour as prices are minimal and offers financial support. A letter of January 8, 1837, discusses their brother, Aquila Janney, and gives the opinion that he is best suited for farming and mentions opportunities for work. A letter of May 17, 1837, discusses Elisha [Janney] and his improvement in health after using the Manchester Mineral Springs, inquires about the building of the mill and mentions financial gains. On June 22, 1842, Janney discusses the city's money affairs being in the worst possible condition and merchants scarcely being able to meet their liabilities. On July 17, 1847, he writes concerning "Israel" and whether or not he will return and expecting to hear from him concerning his whereabouts, the name of his master, and the price to be paid. He also mentions "Armistead" having the objective to solicit aid to purchase his own freedom offered by his master. A letter of October 9, 1848 mentions the death of Nathaniel E. Janney.
Letters, 1837-1840, from Nathaniel E. Janney to Mary Janney chiefly cover personal topics. On March 12, 1837, he expresses thoughts of ending his bachelorhood and getting married, mentions Aquila [Janney] and that Elisha [Janney] has learned his business efficiently. On July 16, 1839, he writes upon hearing of the news of the death of his brother, Charles [Phillips Janney], expressing feelings of grief and also relief for his release from suffering. He also mentions a visit from Robert [H. Miller] and gives advice to James [Janney] on the purchase of wheat. A letter of September 6, 1840 mentions Sarah [Janney] going to Manchester [Mineral Springs] for health reasons, his being confined to work as his two assistants are absent, alternate rains and sunshine yielding the farmers a large return, and business affairs. Janney also writes that he trusts that they shall see elected "the old farmer of North Bend to the Presidency" [William Henry Harrison] (1773-1841).
Letters, 1886-1920, to Thomas Gordon Janney, are chiefly from family members. On October 28, 1886, Charles Phillips Janney writes to his son, inquiring of his studies and mentioning the Circuit Court case Hixson vs. Nixon. Letters, April - May 1918, from Nancy Lee (Janney) Gilmour, discuss her trip to Japan and China. On April 22nd she mentions a visit to the Golden Gate Bridge in San Francisco, California, onboard activities, and people onboard including Dutch, Russians and diplomatic servicemen. On May 1st she mentions a visit to Honolulu, Hawaii, activities onboard including deck tennis, shuffleboard, knitting and reading, celebrating her birthday, and the stunning costumes at the fancy ball from Bolivia, Spain, and Paris. On May 13th she mentions activities in Japan, meeting Japanese dignitaries and other, and being guests at the Embassy. On May 24th, on the Tokyo-Shimonoseki Special, Daily Train de Luxe, she describes scenery from the train, mentions Colonel Robertson, military attache at the British Embassy in Peking, China.
Financial and legal papers, 1695(1755-1873)1906, of the Janney family and others include indentures and other legal documents. There is a document, March 31, 1695, assigning Jacob Janney to be the lawful attorney of his father Thomas Janney. Documents of 1757 relate to bonds between Joseph Yates and Mahlon Janney. A document of July 6, 1780 relates to Fairfax titles. There is the last will and testament, December 8, 1801, of William Darke of Berkeley County. There are indentures of trust, May 2, 1817, between members of the Janney, Osburn and Pursel families concerning a debt to Valentine Pursel and his heirs. There is an indenture, April 3, 1824, between Elisha and Mary Janney and John Janney. A deed, February 10, 1873, concerns property in Loudoun County near the village of Purcellville, and is between members of the Nichols and Janney families.
Miscellaneous correspondence, 1858-1944, n.d., of the Janney and Pollock families cover several topics. There is an interesting letter, September 5, [1858], from Thomas Gordon Pollock (1838-1863) while a student at the University of Virginia. He mentions taking four classes of law and being in his old room at 21 West Lawn. He mentions [Elisha Boyd] Faulkner (1841- ) being there and relates a story about him. He discusses the changes at the University including "an elegant new Hotel built at the end of the Eastern Range with a dining hall..." and describes the new eating arrangements. He also mentions Douglas [French] Forrest (1837- ) taking junior classes of law and being pleased with [James Philemon] Holcombe's (1820-1873) lectures on mercantile law. A letter, February 12, 1908, from Lilias Janney in Pasadena, California, describes the part of town with shops, with all kinds of Indian curios, rugs, baskets, etc. and beautiful China. A letter, Thursday evening [ca. 1908], from George D. Montgomery, Los Angeles, California, to Lilias Janney, mentions a visit to Redondo Beach, Hermosa Beach, Playa del Rey, Venice and Santa Monica and discusses arrangements for Nannie Lee (Pollock) Janney to stay in Pasadena. There is another letter, April 22, 1916, from Lilias Janney in Yokohama, Japan, mentioning a visit to a mission boarding school, describing the living arrangements of the girls at the school, and describing a recital arranged for her in the chapel. A letter of January 17, 1936, from the Friends of the Library of the University of North Carolina discusses the "Southern Collection" of the library.
Other items in this collection include genealogical and historical data, photographs, travel brochures, bound volumes including a photograph album, scrapbook and travel journals. There is also a framed photograph of Robert Stevenson Janney.
Contents List
- Papers of John Janney (1798-1872)
  - Biographical data on John Janney 1890-1938 (Box 1)
  - Civil War Correspondence and Papers of John Janney and Alcinda "Alice" S. (Marmaduke) Janney 1861-1866 (Box 1)
  - Financial and Legal Papers of John Janney 1824-1870, 4 folders (Box 1)
  - Financial and Legal Papers of John Janney 1853-1869 (Box 1)
    re the Alexandria, Loudon, and Hampshire Railroad Company
  - Financial and Legal Papers of John Janney 1796-1842 (Box 1)
    re the Mutual Assurance Society
  - Financial and Legal Papers of John Janney 1809-1859 (Box 1)
    re Thompson & Chinn (deceased) vs. Beveridge
  - Financial and Legal Papers of John Janney 1805-1847 (Box 1)
    re Washington vs. Lovett
  - Memorials and Tributes to John Janney 1872-1925 (Box 1)
  - Personal Correspondence of John Janney and Alcinda "Alice" S. (Marmaduke) Janney 1834-1884 (Box 1)
  - Political Correspondence and Papers of John Janney 1829-1839 (Box 1)
  - Political Correspondence and Papers of John Janney 1840-1858, 16 folders (Box 1)
  - Political Correspondence and Papers of John Janney 1860-1870, n.d., 3 folders (Box 2)
  - Transcripts of Letters from John Janney to Alcinda "Alice" S. (Marmaduke) Janney 1861 Feb-Apr (Box 2)
  - Correspondence of Soloman Parsons [belonging to John Janney' 1810-1830, 3 folders (Box 2)
  - Financial and Legal Papers of Solomon Parsons [belonging to John Janney] 1807-1830 (Box 2)
- Papers of Robert Stevenson Janney
  - Biographical data on Robert Stevenson Janney 1944 (Box 2)
  - Letters concerning Robert Stevenson Janney 1933-1945 (Box 2)
  - Letters from Robert Stevenson Janney to Abraham David Pollock Janney and Lucy (Stevenson) Janney 1924-1943 (Box 2)
  - Letters from Robert Stevenson Janney to Lilias Janney and Nancy Lee (Janney) Gilmour 1925-1943, 3 folders (Box 2)
  - Letters to Robert Stevenson Janney 1915-1930 (Box 2)
  - Letters to Robert Stevenson Janney from Nancy Lee (Janney) Gilmour 1940-1944 (Box 2)
  - Letters to Robert Stevenson Janney from Lilias Janney and Nancy Lee Janney 1928-1929 (Box 2)
  - Mementos 1927-1944, n.d. (Box 2)
    re Robert Stevenson Janney
  - Memorial and Tributes to Robert Stevenson Janney 1944-1951 (Box 2)
  - Certificates awarded to Robert Stevenson Janney by the Royal Life Saving Society 1928, 1930 (Oversize M-22)
  - Certification of the Purple Heart Award to Robert Stevenson Janney 1944 Jun 21 (Oversize M-22)
- Correspondence and Papers of the Gilmour, Janney, and Pollock Families
  - Letters to Abraham David Pollock Gilmour and Nancy Lee (Janney) Gilmour 1897-1946 (Box 3)
  - Letters to Abraham David Pollock Gilmour and Nancy Lee (Janney) Gilmour from his children 1934-1944, n.d., 2 folders (Box 3)